all right everybody good evening uh
welcome to our all hands call uh joining
us this evening are some of the most
influential thought leaders from the
health insurance sector we have with us
uh mr anurak kumar miss malti jaswal and
mr birendra mohanty who will be
discussing
health insurance for india's missing
middle
the call will begin with anurag taking
us through a paper he co-authored while
at neeti io last year followed by a
fireside chat with miss ashwal and mr
mohanty now the primary purpose of this
report is to recognize the policy issue
of low financial protection for health
in the missing middle segment
the report highlights health insurance
as a potential pathway in addressing
that and in improving the efficacy and
quality of the healthcare that is
delivered in doing so the report offers
a starting point for broader discussions
on solutions specific products to
improve insurance coverage for the
missing middle the report envisages a
wider industry and government
stakeholder consultation as well as
discussion with consumer groups to delve
deeper into specific components of the
problem as well as forging a potential
path ahead before we delve into the call
uh a note for the attendees uh we do
hope to accommodate all questions and uh
questions that you might have um please
do either of the following type your
question in the q a box which will be
activated or raise your hand we shall
try to accommodate
all questions uh in case we are not able
to you can always mail your questions to
us at the email id that has been
provided which is all hands at
firstup.org
before we begin i would also like to
briefly introduce our speakers for the
day
starting with anurag he currently works
as a healthy economist at the world bank
prior to this he worked on health
financing and economics related policy
issues at epio his interest areas
include financing mechanisms public
policy formulation and the role of the
private sector
he holds an mba economics and public
policy from princeton university and a b
tech from iit delhi thank you for
joining us
next we have malty mam with us uh marty
jaswal has worked in the insurance
industry since 1986 and has contributed
to setting the foundations for health
insurance in india during 2014-18 she
served as the chief operating officer
with the health insurance cpa of india
in 2018 multiman joined the world bank
where she has worked on ap abp and jy as
a senior consultant since she developed
a diploma certification course on health
insurance for the insurance institute of
india she's also a member of the health
forum of irdai and also led the irdai
nha joint working group on fraud and
abuse control thank you for joining us
ma'am
finally we have birendra with us
berendra is an insurance professional
with over 21 years of work experience he
is an associate of insurance from the
insurance institute of india and
currently heads distribution practices
of icici lombard dic india's second
largest insurance company where he is
currently responsible for agency and sme
thank you sir for joining us uh
with that um i hand over the floor to
anurag uh
you may begin thank you so much
thank you shimangi and thank you to this
first team aj
for having me
um
i think sort of the organization of our
health system or our health sector in
general is one of the most important
issues sort of as we look in the next 10
to 20 years
um as a country so anything which deals
with how it's organized in terms of the
purchasers the providers the regulator
and most importantly the patient
discussing that and arriving at
solutions is very important so thanks
for organizing that in
in that context and before i get into it
i think just very quick to disclaimers
as you've already mentioned these
uh views are my own they're not my
current employers world bank or of vpios
having said that this report is a
government of india report which was
prepared
when i was there
so let's um get into it next slide
please
so the idea is basically i'll outline
some key messages which came out of the
report and in doing so i'll start with a
bit of the background and context why
we're talking about this then what does
the current health insurance landscape
look like what are some of the
characteristics of the people who we
think are not covered and then really
get into the solution space and
potential pathways right uh what would a
product what would such a product be
what are some of the key challenges and
what are some of the solutions that we
can think of
and then really get into discussions and
questions with uh malty and bender who
know about this much more than i do so i
think
so we leave more time for the most
interesting part so next slide please
so in terms of
background and context right why are we
talking about it so if we look at
india's health financing landscape but
the government spending on health both
in absolute terms is quite low and as a
share is around one third of the total
now this obviously has implications in
terms of
uh the capacity of the government
providers to deliver you see overcrowded
hospitals etc but what it also means
is that most of the spending around
two-thirds is private and not only is it
private it's mostly out of pocket right
so most of the two-thirds private
spending is almost all out of pocket if
you see sort of the chart to the right
and the dark blue line at the top is
india you'll see it's been persistent
around
over 60 60 to 70 percent over the last
decade which is higher than the lower
middle income country average it's
higher than the middle income average
and it's higher than the global average
uh and what that means is
and sort of all of this out of pocket
expenditure is with private providers
predominantly right with an unclear link
to what kind of outcomes are being
provided what kind of quality it is so
that's why this is something that we
really need to think about so why health
insurance right in this context so two
things right one
uh which i think everyone knows and
recognizes is that it provides financial
protection from health shocks right you
pool funds so you're cross-subsidizing
um from the healthy to the sick from
sort of the young to the old et cetera
et cetera i think the second point which
is a little bit less appreciated but i
think is quite important as we think
about more outcomes in the organization
of the system is that
when you have
an insurer or when you have sort of a
consolidated pool of funds by a
purchaser instead of individuals
going for consultations going for
discrete things at the hospital
it improves efficiency of spending right
because then you can negotiate packages
you can avoid wastage in terms of doing
the same test twice a different part so
and those are the kinds of provider
consolidation and sort of improving
efficiency of spending which which a
purchaser can provide so these are the
two fundamental reasons why health
insurance can be one step in pathway
it's not the only thing uh the
government spending increase is super
important but that's sort of the context
in which to frame this conversation
um going to the next slide please
so just to say i mean again in terms of
financial hardship which is one
component of financial protection
different estimates but around five to
nine people go into poverty uh from
out-of-pocket expenditure on health
around a quarter of the population
spends more than 10 percent of their
household income and health and of those
who access health care almost
60 percent end up paying more than ten
percent of their household income on
health and these are huge numbers
because it's not like the first three
four quintiles have a lot of disposable
income
um next slide please
so what does the current insurance
landscape look like right who is covered
who's not covered what their
characteristics
next slide
so currently
you can think of the health insurance
landscape is basically there's three
broad kinds of provision the biggest
chunk is government subsidized health
insurance and this is eligibility not
necessarily a coverage and i'll come to
what that means around 50 crore people
are covered by adp mji which is the
centrally sponsored scheme right this
five are eligible sorry which is um
which is the centrally sponsored scheme
the five lakh per family cover
then in addition to this there are 20
crore which are eligible or covered
under state extension schemes so these
are
states which choose to extend either the
number of people covered and sometimes
they also expand the
benefits package
so you have around 70 crore people who
are in principle eligible for government
subsidized health insurance scheme then
you have around 14 crore people who have
social health insurance so in this the
biggest chunk is mostly the employee
state insurance scheme which is for
formal sector workers earning less than
21 000 in in firms of a certain scale
right so this the employer pays and the
employee pays a contribution and then
they get access to some services and
then the third chunk is private
voluntary health insurance which
includes both group insurance and family
insurance basically the retail product
that you buy which is around 11 and a
half crore so if you add these up
it's around 95 throw
people who are either eligible or
covered with health insurance right
which leaves around 40
now two things to highlight one sort of
um
this is a mix of different insurance
schemes obviously and the benefits
packages are very different so it
doesn't mean everyone gets covered by a
same set of benefits or has access to
the same quality of care most of them
have no phd or opd benefits except esis
in principle the second thing is actual
coverage might be
um lower it might be around 50 instead
of 70 percent and this is because of gap
in eligibility and coverage in the
government subsidized insurance schemes
uh due to a bunch of reasons potential
overlap between different schemes and
the final point is we're talking about
coverage or eligibility but
there's also this point to be noted that
that doesn't necessarily translate into
access and quality of care right that
doesn't mean that you're covered that
you can you necessarily have the places
to go and
uh because there's also a supply side
dimension to it
all right so i mean either way if it's
40 crore if it's 50 crore at 60 crore
there is a large number of people who
are uncovered so who are these people
next slide
so normally the way that we think about
the missing middle or it's been
conceived is sort of to the left-hand
side right is that there is a poor which
is covered by government subsidized
health insurance then there is a
relatively rich which is covered uh
which is mostly formal or organized
sector covered by private voluntary
health insurance and shi and the missing
middle is somewhere in the
uh in between as the name suggests
but
in reality it's much more of a triangle
or a diamond with uh with sort of it
being spread across different income
categories but really concentrated in
that third to fifth income quintile um
is sort of how you would actually
think of it and so the idea is just to
say that the missing middle refers to a
diverse
it's not a monolith it refers to sort of
a broad area of groups and some of them
will have some financial capacity to pay
based on where they sit
next slide please
so just broadly in terms of where it's
spread and this is sort of a lot of
number crunching and then some sort of
estimates based on nsso data uh but just
to say that it is spread across rural
and urban areas um an estimated 27 to 35
crore individuals in rural areas 11 to
13 crew were in urban areas
in the rural areas they would be
predominantly self-employed in
agriculture or self-employed in
non-agricultural activities and then
around and then a few who are wage
earners
in the urban
setting it's much more diverse it will
be formal semi-formal and informal
sector right so you can think of people
in the formal sector very clearly having
an ability to pay but they feel that
they don't get any value out of it or
it's just not worth it right you can
think of a lot of young people uh you
yeah
then there are people in the semi-formal
and informal sector where probably
awareness um is sort of a bigger concern
and these could be everyone to
people working in your household uh they
could be
people sitting in small shops they could
be painters welders plumbers etc etc
um so just to say it spread across
google urban areas income groups and and
a diverse area of occupations next slide
please
so so yeah we know sort of
how this problem is framed now why it's
important what are some of the
characteristics of the people who are
not included so let's get into the
solution space and potential pathways
where we can go from here what are some
of the things that we need to think
about next slide
so there are three fundamental elements
uh that that we thought of
um while while thinking about the
solution
the first is the product right so the
first question to ask is all right so
what kind of benefits are we offering
and what will be the cost of this
product and this wasn't something that
sort of came up more theoretically this
was a working group
which included a lot of different
insurers it included a lot of private
sector participants and it was based on
those discussions in terms of what might
be feasible the second is then who is
the insurer or purchaser right is it
is it predominantly through private
commercial insurers as a contributory
product should government purchasers
esic or the national health authority
play a role and the third is the
financing agent will it be affordable to
the private customer um
or whether partial or full government
subsidy may be required so these are
sort of the three
broad blocks to think of as we move into
the solution space next slide please
right so
existing private voluntary health
products are a bit expensive for example
for a family of four to five they would
be around twelve to twenty four thousand
if we think um
of the affordability of the missing
middle this is around two to three x
that price point right and we'll get
into a bit of how we came to that uh a
bit later so what does
and and then we think of all right based
on these discussions that we had in the
working committee what does a product
look like so one there were two things
which were clear one is standardization
and simplicity right that health
insurance is a complex product to
understand sort of for anyone there's
things there's exclusions there are
waiting periods uh there are deductibles
there are co-pays it's not an easy thing
to understand so you need some sort of
standardization of benefits and
simplicity so there's a broad idea of
these are the kinds of things that we
will get and then to have paper lesson
cashless coverage etc to reduce that
complexity the second is in terms of
affordability which we talked about and
for an ipd product four to six thousand
per family per year and around five
thousand for an opd sort of subscription
model is what what would seem to uh make
sense from these consultations
um next slide please
right so in terms of the product itself
right and first we'll focus on the ipd
or the hospitalization part of the
product there's already something which
adai launched called arugia sanjeevani
which aims to create a standardized
product with a defined minimum
benefits package
it's hospital cover only but it just
says that this is the waiting period
these are the set of benefits these are
what is excluded these are the limits
this is the copay so it has the sum in
short is flexible depending on need but
it gives some structure that
irrespective of where you buy it from
this is what you're assured now the
subscription to this has been quite low
it's less than one percent of uh the
entire private voluntary health
insurance market
and that could be due to a variety of
reasons so we think like that's a good
start
the proposed product would probably
should have lower waiting periods and
then consider instead of fee for service
some package rates to maybe reduce the
overall cost
but that's something that it can build
on there's more details sort of of what
the product is proposed in the report
but but that i think is the starting
point uh next slide
so then and this is i think a very
important point is in terms of having
opd cover think that for the missing
middle having an opd cover would be
quite important
obviously it's easier said than done but
for two reasons one is to reduce
catastrophic health so basically for all
your financial hardship and financial
protection and the second is to increase
the products update and this is because
of the following reason right for people
who incur catastrophic health
expenditures so for people who spend or
households which spend more than 10
percent of the sold income
on health
almost 80 percent do so on outpatient
and around 40 do an inpatient it's
greater than 100 because some people do
it on board so which basically means
that
people who are affected or for whom
financial hardship occurs due to health
opd expenses are much more salient than
ipd and secondly only three to four
percent of people have an ipd visit
every year right maximum five percent
whereas opd visits are much more common
around two per person per year so the
perceived value of the product increases
if you're at least utilizing something
um and then again this point which
relates to what i started with
integrating ipd and opd can also lead to
overall efficiency right reducing cost
improving outcomes it means that again
you're not repeating the diagnostic test
you're thinking about treating at the
right level you're going to the clinic
or the gp instead of the hospital
there's some more incentive alignment
between the different providers and then
there is some sort of initial skeleton
of what could be
uh of what could be an opt product next
slide please
so now coming back to this four to six
thousand number and five thousand that
we discussed one way to think about what
is affordable is to look at what is the
current average out of pocket spending
that a family of five would do right and
we look at it both in urban and rural
areas in the third to fifth expenditure
quintiles assuming that the first two
are mostly covered uh through government
subsidized health insurance so you can
see sort of the red box shows that
around two and a half thousand to six
and a half thousand is what on an
average a family of five would spend
on out of pocket expenditure on ipd so
then this four to six thousand premium
makes sense obviously your willingness
to pay will be much lower because not
everything is covered and an outpatient
similarly the spending is around between
5000 to 10 000. now again everything
won't be covered so 5000 seemed like uh
the base and seemed like a good starting
point
but but just to say that there is this
is what they're already paying on an
average so there is
uh affordability in that sense now what
the willingness to pay is is what we'll
get into sort of during the discussion
next slide please
um yeah just then in terms of the
challenges right so
there are three challenges which i think
we all know but just sort of to outline
them and then think about who has to
solve these challenges first is
awareness and confidence in health
insurance while you discuss that
insurance is a complex product you pay
for it in the hope to not use it which
is sort of not a very intuitive way of
spending right so a lot of consumer
education is required to increase uptake
and this is the role of both the
government and the private sector in our
opinion
the second is to build confidence in
existing products right if you have good
grievance to wrestle then you have a lot
of word and mouth and then
sort of that also includes the update of
the product now this is the role of the
regulator in terms of the enforcement
and the role of the private sector in
terms of sort of
delivering what is promised
then the second is reducing the cost for
affordability and this is about one
reducing distribution and operational
cost which
around 30 to 40 percent of the premiums
sort of go into distribution and
operational cost right so
and so leveraging digital channels for
distribution can we think of improving
operational efficiency and claims
processing these are uh two things to
think about and then
uh when we have these ipd opd integrated
models
um then we can also think about more
efficiencies which reduce costs further
and the final point is sort of a classic
health insurance uh private sorry
voluntary health insurance issue is of
adverse selection which is basically the
sickest people enrolled which means the
premiums keep on going up as healthy
people opt out and then conversely
preferred selection which is then
insurers would want to exclude some of
the riskiest people or to price them out
and
and then sort of that defeats the
purpose of health insurance so the only
way out of this is to have a large
diversified risk crew and then it's
thinking about what are some of these
formal and informal groups that we can
address and what has been the success
what have been the challenges of it
right vendor association self-help
groups uh et cetera et cetera to
diversify the risk which can also then
bring down the cost because then you're
not subsidizing because you're reducing
adverse elections so it's also bringing
down the cost uh which which goes to
point
so wrapping up i think uh next slide
then what are some of the potential
models right as we think about this what
are some of the potential models so
going back to the framing of this if we
think
on a 2x2 scale
the government or a private purchaser or
agency and then who finances it whether
the government or the private
individuals finance it one model is to
expand fully subsidized coverage to part
of the missing middle through pmjyou
basically basically expanded this is
completely government finance government
done
the second is that
um the existing network so the national
health authority or esic
introduce what they offer as a voluntary
product right so in the case of eic asic
it would be their medical benefits which
are offered as a voluntary contributory
product in addition to what they
currently do in the case of pmji they
can offer their existing product to
people who want to buy it a pmj plus
which is on the lines of a proposed
product so this is privately financed
but government purchasing
and the third is what we talked is then
the private insurer is sort of offering
this modified rogues and genie product
with opt so these are the three sort of
broad things that we think about um in
in terms of expanding insurance coverage
and next slide which is the final slide
how do we think about it right perhaps
in terms of a time frame
in the short term maybe we think about
and see
whether this expanding private voluntary
insurance through commercial insurers
work essentially this product which
we've talked about
and then the role of the government and
the private sector is building consumer
awareness offering this product having
large group enrollments to sort of build
large diverse schools and increasing the
affordability
in the medium term we can think about
offering of opening up nha pmji and esic
to offer a voluntary product now the
reason why
hurry into doing this is that there are
already a lot of challenges uh in terms
of utilization of pmji and esic on the
supply side to start with and on the
demand side so you don't want to add on
more things to their existing mission
without sort of
uh the core function being strong and so
this is something which once that once
their core function stabilizes is
something that
and this will again increase the
competition potentially lower prices and
in the long term
there might be a certain segment which
cannot
afford to have voluntary insurance and
so then we think about expanding
subsidized insurance under emj to those
populations
uh so i'll end with that just one thing
sort of this will be in a sense a
uniquely indian solution because the
classic textbook tells you that the
voluntary health insurance sort of with
an informal labor market is
is extremely difficult it's very
difficult to work anywhere so
what we discuss in terms of building
these risk pools in terms of lowering
the prices will have to be sort of a
uniquely indian solution there isn't as
much global precedent to it countries in
southeast asia latin america china have
tried some of this and it's um and
there's mixed results but
so i'll also sort of end with that
caveat
um thank you
there's few discussion questions which i
think i have on a couple of slides later
if you want to get but that's where
thank you everyone
thank you uh so much uh anurag for
secondly summarizing where or the
current landscape is how we got here how
this is a uniquely
indian problem and an indian solution uh
before we begin
uh the process of the dialogue i would
first like to hear the thoughts of our
other speakers as well um uh multi ma'am
uh i'll hand it over to you for the next
few minutes
yeah thank you thank you and uh that was
a very good uh you know very
comprehensive presentation of a very
nicely done report
and
so i think all the all the key issues
have been you know kind of uh
raised in that report may not be you
know addressed because as you as you
operationalize something you know then
the then the the practical issues on
ground issues also emerge
a few points that i would like to make
is that
the complexity of of covering everybody
you know i think we could be a little
less ambitious that let's say that let's
cover
more people and have a time frame of you
know let's say you know five years to
achieve that so maybe then you know then
then we may be a little more you know
you know realistic in you know what
could be achieved and you know what
could be you know done
a voluntary or mandatory of course you
know pre-paid large pool panda tree is
what you know would everyone would tell
us and every insurer's dream would be to
you know every every person in india is
told to buy health insurance
but mandation doesn't happen you know
when even as i was giving example of you
know motor insurance even even though
mandatory and by law required there are
so many vehicles uninsured particularly
the tubular segment or the commercial
vapors
correct so i think we will have to look
for solutions which are in between you
know these two extremes of voluntary and
mandatory and how do you increase the
uptake
and you know provided that we do come up
with an affordable product which every
insurer you know
let's say that let's let's imagine for a
moment that there was a base product
available to every indian like a
modified version of arugula sanjivani
let's say clone of pmj i would for
better words you know let's say clone of
pmj because pmj is very affordable
compared to our pcg if you look at the
you know the cost that uh you know pmj
is having some of the burning cost of
the premiums uh it's very affordable
compared to our usually so let's say
that if we were to you know if
government of india along with irda
along with nha was to come up with a you
know standard product like clone of pmj
offered on nha platform you know with
all all the hospital network all the you
know packages you know health benefit
packages so there is an advantage of you
know
in there would be an automatic
uh jump start you know advantage of you
know having so many things in place for
a large large you know you know product
affordable product
then how do you popularize it how do you
make it make it you know
get you know purchased by people you
know who for whom
help may be a priority after probate but
they they still feel why you know i'm
healthy you know why do i need even even
you know richer segments you know the
young people think like this so then
there is no you know
uh
nothing to be held against people that
who feel that by the way
so i feel that there have to be couple
of things you know which could help in
addressing this issue one would be that
let's you know now building an element
of opd is very very you know easy with
the digital health coming up with abdm
coming up that is one digital health
mission coming up so once we build an
opd element they would automatically be
a greater pull to the product you know
hospitalization doesn't attract anyone i
may not fall sick i mean you know
all those things number one
number two you know encouraging people
how do how do you encourage people and
third would be how do you avoid adverse
election so any adverse selection you
could avoid by offering this product to
groups only in the beginning don't offer
it on a retail basis don't offer it on
individual basis and groups could be
formed for for you know resident welfare
association or a or inmates association
or you know any informal worker any any
kind of groups but that would be
definitely required to you know
subsidize from you know you know age to
young and you know healthy to sick so
that groups you know that was some
concept that we were trying to do in nha
in missing middle that only offering it
to the groups for safety of you know
adverse election
third making it you know how do you how
do you have the you know uptake
increased so in this update i would say
that if there was uh let's say that you
know in india we are very conscious of
the price and you know we are very
attracted by free
free element there is something
available free you know sales discount
all right you know so i think if if
working on that mindset if we could
offer it you know uptake by 20 discount
30 discount you enroll within this
period you know from the groups i think
and that discount
kind of is is coming up from the from
the you know subsidy that the large
number would provide that discount need
not be you know funded by by somebody
external to the risk pool you know the
pool itself should fund that discount
would be that kind of figure of concept
so these are two or three things you
know at a bigger yeah i think let's say
you know
what do you say at a
whiteboard kind of a stage if if these
three four things are worked out and i
think the nithya yoga has set up a
committee you know for for looking into
the you know coming up with solutions
for missing middleware insurance
industry is a part ird is a part so i i
i'm sure you know we'll have some
solutions like this coming up yeah thank
you
thank you so much from uh
over to you yeah yeah uh great
presentation
and very well articulated by multi-mah
let me say this is a very unique problem
of missing middle basically it's
basically something which is
regulatory acceptable when i say
regulator actually simplicity of the
product
it has to be socially desirable like we
say basically there's a desire from the
government from the insurers from
everybody that's desirable out there it
also has to be technological physical we
have not talked about how do you make
the scale of reach of 40 crore families
or particular individuals i mean in
terms of using the technologically doing
it and of course financially viable for
the insurers because unless until the
scale is there and it is financially
viable you see what happened in arugu
sanjivani i mean i mean what basically
the numbers were not there in arugula as
a product and of course
i mean what anurag said about it about
in terms of affordability of the
customer as well that has to be equally
affordable to the customer or the
individuals out there uh a lot of things
we have done in the past uh i mean a lot
of innovations and technology work has
happened in the past we can take a lot
of cues from that for example uh we used
to launch uh we used to do a weavers and
artisans policies which is basically
social groups i mean at that point of
time uh some 17 18 lakhs families were
insured and three lakhs are fully around
actions and so on now if you see that
product at that point of time probably
in 2010-11 we launched that product uh
that was opt cover uh and the product
was customized to the requirements of
the viewers and artisans for example
normally viewers and artisans used to
have asthma i mean because they are on
day in day out being
i mean with those environment we had a
specific coverage around that and the
some insurance was higher out there so i
mean
similar things happened in rsby for
example one of the biggest challenge in
rsbi was affordability i mean common
subsidy was there and itself the scale
was achieved and competition led the
price from 1000 rupees per card to some
300 400 pistol card so that means there
are multiple ways i mean the point i
want to bring in is uh this is a segment
which may or may not require a subsidy
of the government i mean we'll have to
use uh that is affordability we'll have
to construct a product which is viable
and then actually use technology and
innovation to scale and then make it
affordable rather than subsidizing and
making it affordable because anything
which is in a subsidy in a long term 40
crores individuals i mean honestly it
will be a big challenge for the
extracurricular for any
part of the country i mean it will be
difficult out there
from the insurer's point of view one of
the biggest challenge of course is how
do you create a large risk pool because
unless until there is a reduction of the
adverse elections that risk pool will
actually observe the risk out there and
uh without scale uh i mean it will not i
mean the the missing middle will always
remain missing i mean how do you ensure
that the insurers play a big part and we
create affordable product and build a
scale which then takes care of the
product rather than subsidizing those
products i think these are some of the
initial thoughts i thought i will share
okay thank
i would like to make additional point
which i i think i missed is another
another very important stakeholder and
this is the private health care
providers
i think taking them a long way because
no insurance product no more health
insurance product can be viable can be
sustainable can be feasible without
buying it of the private health care
providers
and and making them agree to because
they have a different costing mechanisms
from where the cost is coming cost is
cost of health insurance is coming
basically from the claims cost you know
the utilization cost so it's is one one
element is a is a smaller risk pool but
the other other
other element which is beyond the
control of insurance industry is the you
know is the cost of care is the cost of
care so
having a buying in from the private
providers
at
prices of costs which are for you know
sustainable for them
and helping them you know
achieve more efficiencies in their own
business you know having some kind of a
uh you know aggregated you know
purchasing done for them you know to
bring down their own cost of you know
inputs is very very important element
where you know
a collective you know work by all the
stakeholders by the you know
bodies like nha or you know and irda and
private insurance industry and private
providers all have to collectively come
and think about it
yeah
correct
all right we have quite a few questions
lined up so i will try my uh best to go
through each of them i think the first
one is addressed to anurag uh mr
manjunathankar has asked higher opd
fees may be due to increased episodes
per annum or are they due to doctor
shopping was it controlled for each opd
episode which required admission
uh you're on youtube yeah sorry can you
hear me now
yeah
so this is basically uh it doesn't look
at whether those opts turn into ipds you
you can track that but this is just to
say that these are the number of opts
and this is what is being spent and
these are the number of ipds now even if
you take out the opd's which turned into
ipt still the opd component would be
large right because ipd's is only three
to four percent so you can add on any
amount of opd but it wouldn't
um sort of change that calculus it's
basically like the volume of opd's and
the frequency with which it happens
which which drives that number
okay
the next question we have from dr
uh he has asked which of the below
models in your understanding is the best
suited for india
the nhs uk single-payer system the copay
system that germany has or the publicly
funded and privately delivered system in
canada while he has issues long waiting
time making healthcare delivery more
complex
let me take it up yeah sure yeah uh so
all we believe is uh always in india
every uh unique model i mean i mean
every point of time um what has happened
i mean let me give some examples i mean
so that
i mean for example uh when we started
doing rsby at that point of time uh we
thought about saying doing a cashless
card i mean today the technology is much
evolved i mean probably at that point of
time you don't have all those uh
mobile being linked to jonathan accounts
and other things so i mean
in india if you ask me that is a
relevant infrastructures from technology
point of view from scale point of view
from digital point of view we have to
use our infrastructure what is available
with in our countries and our level of
innovation stood structure uh probably
that will help us to build it faster
rather than copying any other models
all right i'll move on to the third one
just very very quickly to add is that in
all of these models i mean the
government spending
um to gdp ratio is around eight or nine
percent we spend one and a half percent
right so
like there is
for any of these models to be successful
there is that gap or you have to have a
very high formal share of the labor
market it's almost 100 or 90 there we
have almo we have 10
so that's where these models sort of
break down
and for us i think uh it will have to be
a
a an indian model and we will have to
kind of come up with a you know you know
indian model
you know is something you know which is
unique which is frugal which is you know
you know takes into account of the
complexities of this you know we are a
huge country you know and we have to
also take into account you know health
is a state subject and the between the
states there are variations of the
health system being at the top or you
know being you know nowhere so i think
these are the complexities which make
you know one one solution so it will
have to be
even within india we can't have one
solution for all all types of states so
adopting a country's model which is you
know which is you know presently i sit
in canada and i and i hear people out
you know that they are not happy with
the system so i i came to a conclusion
that nobody is happy with their health
system you know that maybe that's that's
the truth in india we grip about private
care and all that here people are
cribbing about long waiting periods
doctors are not available and kovid has
you know of course you know uh
catapulted lot you know issues you know
in the public health systems so i think
no health system we would be able to
adopt as it is we will have to come up
and in fact
it is happening already we are coming up
with our own solutions you look at the
digital health space i think is one of
the most vibrant space in india compared
to anywhere i think uh the the digital
health space the startups and the
solutions that they're coming up with
yeah
thank you before i move on to the next
question in the chat box actually
prameskar has raised his hand uh sir i
think you're on you've been unmuted
please go ahead and ask your question
yeah thank you thank you
uh
i just have one question for all the
panelists
uh we all speak about how big a country
india is how difficult it is to scale it
up
we've had several excuses about how
is it is the basic problem the fact that
we spend far too less on public health
care expenditure and are we just uh
looking at excuses to uh uh avoid this
very uncomfortable truth
you want to go first
sure i'm happy to either um look i would
completely agree with you i mean no
questions asked right our
share of spending uh towards gdp to our
government expenditure is one of the
lowest in the world right and especially
for things which are preventive care
which is uh which are public goods which
have a lot of externalities contact
tracing disease surveillance and also
like for for fundamental health care you
would need to spend a lot more so
this was sort of framed in the context
of if that lever is not moving or not
moving fast enough we inch by point one
percent of the gdp every two odd years
but if that's not moving fast enough
then what are some of the other
solutions given this how out of pocket
expenditure burden but
yes if that happens that is sort of
definitely uh one of them so there is so
there is no denying uh you know that
you know spending on health care has to
go up
but uh another harsh fact would be it
hasn't gone up
right so what do you do then you know do
we keep on hoping that it will go up and
you know what would be then or maybe
come up as another oxygen solution that
that liver doesn't move what else could
be done i think
we have you know somehow made may not be
ideal but moved into that space where
let's look at solutions you know what
could be done you know with that lever
staying where it is and maybe inching
you know very slowly to make it make an
impact otherwise that would be nothing
better than that to happen you know uh
apologies for interrupting again but i
think if we
accept this i think we are going down a
very slippery slope and we are
condemning our society to a situation
where
uh it is hopeless
and
trying to make the best of what we can i
think that's that's that's not an
acceptable solution
uh
okay so i think uh
i would say that
i won't
paint a doom scenario because of this
you know there have been so many
learnings and there have been you know
many learnings you know any program when
rsby started people's book like you know
people said you know private health care
you know private health insurance is no
solution when pmj started you know
people
but i think we also got to admit that
need hospitalization cover you know they
need primary care they need you know
public health they also need you know dr
industrial famously i think one of the
you know interviews he gave he said what
do you do about people who are you know
you know getting hospitalized you know
how do you how do you you know kind of
reduce the shock for them so it it is it
is i won't say that
it's a doom scenario but i would say
it's a solution which is you know which
is
uh you know implementable in the in the
short run i would i would agree that if
there was a long-term solution which
builds a pathway connections and how
this you know seamlessly integrates into
into a bigger health health systems you
know a kind of a you know situation that
would be really really good but i i
think with all the learnings that we
have with the digital health platforms
that we have with nha being in place
and you know a lot of things that that
are a lot of pieces to the puzzle which
are in place i think we are in in better
place to you know kind of embark on this
uh private health insurance is
is actually not looked upon as a
solution and i don't think we are
offering it as a solution to you know
what else you know or whatever be the
issues with the health systems at a
wider level but i think it's a solution
which is available which is you know
which which is you know feasible
operationally
fiscally in many ways you know compared
to you know a long-term you know and
i think i at my age stage i have become
more realistic let's say that
right i'll move on uh to the next
question dr chintan maru has asked
transforming the relationship between
the payer and provider can be a big
driver of affordability that can be
achieved through managed care
value-based purchasing vertically
integrated payer provider integration
and other models as well what is the
feasibility slash timeline on testing
some of these options in the indian
context
do you want to go first
oh yeah
the relationship
yeah so i mean as mam said earlier i
mean uh provider has to be an integral
part of this i mean there is no way uh i
mean we can develop a model uh i mean to
involve a missing i mean middle two
being short uh that is this is a big
challenge in terms of pair provider
model in terms of affordability and
but steps are being taken at this point
of time and what it was earlier and
currently what steps are being taken by
the regulator by the government this is
a gradual process it will not open i
mean happen overnight or other things
but things are being put in place i
think i am positive about it that in the
long run this will be a viable model
because until unless this pair provided
model is stabilized and it's makes
viable further from the affordable point
of view it will be a big challenge even
though irdi has also issued a lot of i
mean notifications regulations around
managing this in the long run it will
fall in place ma'am over two
yeah i think private provider
relationship would never be you know
easy it would always be you know pulling
each other you know the other from the
different ends and so it'd be i think
that that is all right so long as they
have patients in trust in mind so long
as patient and policyholder whatever you
call it beneficial you know by whatever
name but the person who's receiving care
funding is everyone is providing and one
other one is funding provided we have
the interest of the you know customer or
the patient in mind there would be a
meeting point i think the meeting point
is missing because of many things in
india like there are no regulations for
health care insurance industries highly
regulated or you know that quality of
care there's so many issues surrounding
health care in india which is you know
non-standardized some of the areas are
now getting standardized and we are
having standard treatment guidelines and
protocols but otherwise there have been
many issues and then i think private
care itself has it has its own you know
challenges of of you know getting
talented people and you know cost of
care managing efficiencies
and of course they are corporatized i
think we should not forget that so once
the corporatization or any
industrialization of a of a service like
health care happens some things are
inevitable to happen
all right
thank you ma'am we'll move on to the
next question from dr anjum shay how
about introducing preventive health care
in the product which will help to keep
population healthy and this in turn will
lead to less uh outgoing from payers for
hospitalization claims and even
privately in shock private insurance can
take part in extended coverage in lower
premium
that's impressive
or to whom
uh whoever wants to take it please
go ahead please yeah uh so i mean uh
preventive care or opd as a segment
honestly a lot more insurers have
started launching products around that
uh but the biggest challenge is how do
you link your opd with your ipd i mean
till the time uh there is a direct
correlation of opd leading to lower ipd
that probably that's a question marks
which remain i mean there have been some
successes around there but uh eventually
i mean these are these are things which
will early to do that the biggest one of
the other challenges in the preventive
care or specifically opd as a segment is
one of the that's probably one of the
biggest areas of fraud even i mean we
have seen uh i mean a lot of the fraud
happening opening up much higher in
operating than even ipd so a lot of
technologies solutions have also evolved
in those lines
how do you i mean i mean
how to solve this problem of opt that's
probably one of the biggest step because
ipd you have much more control i mean
the person is hospitalized you have much
more control over there opt there is a
challenge of fraud out there and uh the
scale also i mean probably there uh if
you don't achieve a scale uh i mean it
becomes inherently difficult to manage
the so those are two broad challenges
about opd and preventive care
uh can i add something to
another you know perspective to this so
i think opd is is prone to prone to
abuse you know because you know every
one of us is anxious to see a doctor at
drop of a hat you know if we have you
know free access so i think now with
technology available with
teleconsultation being available you
know telemedicine being available you
can have a layered opd you know you
don't you know don't expose the you know
the whole ecosystem in one go and then
one leads to the other and refers to the
other
in that way but as i said everyone in
the ecosystem has to work together for
such an ideal solution to operate you
know efficiently for all and you know
for this but i think
i'm very
confident that this could this can
happen because of the digital you know
infrastructure that we have created and
we are creating in the country you know
so i think that is the going to be the
backbone of creating uh this kind of an
ecosystem and for that the foundation is
being laid so that's how i'm pretty
confident that opd can be a very you
know an ex extremely uh useful solution
from the patient perspective also you
know the anxiety to see a doctor so you
have a health line a nurse helpline or
something you know which leads to them
to the consultation then to the medical
tests you know all those you know
solutions
could be actually at least piloted if
not you know large scale implementation
may happen later but it could be
violated in one or two districts
just very quickly to add when we speak
of uh preventive care there's also the
larger public health element right like
a lot of preventive care isn't
individual a lot of it has to do with
water and sanitation things which are
beyond the remit of the ministry of
health per se uh it has to do with
nutrition they're extremely extremely
strong links between nutrition and
health um yeah so in that sense like
these are fundamental either public
goods or things which have very large
positive externalities which probably
the government has to invest in but yes
within sort of individual uh insurance
there's all these things which which
were outlined so just that framing
i i want to uh go next to a question
being posed by nippon with money uh
given group products tend to largely be
unprofitable in health how does one
ensure that they are sustainable
how does one shot can you just repeat
uh given that group products tend to
largely be unprofitable in health how
does one ensure that they are
sustainable as well
so uh let me uh answer that you know
very first and you can you know add if i
miss you know uh so group products are
an unsustainable is a notion that we
have in india due to few particular you
know scenarios that happen you know
which is basically public sector
insurance companies you know giving a
very wide you know luxurious and you
know
no holds bar kind of a cover at a price
which is unsustainable that's what is
making the group covers and sustainable
nothing else is making the group if you
look at the group covers offered by the
you know other insurance companies it's
basically the public sector insurance
companies and we need to bring kind of a
and that's a good question also that we
need to kind of rein in the the lux the
luxury element or the hoteling element
of you know care which you know some of
these products tend to offer you know
and which is you know which is you know
making it unaffordable you know and then
there are elements like you know
covering the you know parents in the
same group and you know
giving every possible cover on uh you
know in the in the cupboard
so i think that is what is making it
unsustainable it's not inherently
unsustainable we made it in
unsustainable by our own you know
wrongful underwriting practices if we
were to do good underwriting it should
it wouldn't be unsustainable
so
yeah i'll just add to my few words
our ability to price group health or
group and writing is
there seems to be an audio issue
with your microphone
no
so i think the point uh perhaps if i
caught uh you know if i could catch the
words that he you know
some of the keywords the availability of
actuarial data is another essential
element to pricing of care you know so
in in in india historically our data
collection has not been that strong
and you know are
in the industry needs you know more
actuarial data you know for pricing of
you know products correctly
but in groups i would say that it's it's
less of actuarial pricing but you know
it's
neck to neck the actual utilization
versus the premium you know so there is
very risk very less risk element as such
in groups you know which which we see in
the market is
basically estimating the outgos the you
know incidence and the severity you know
like how many people will fall sick and
what will be the severity of that
sickness is basically estimating that
actuarial risk as such i group groups i
don't think is a risk carrying function
it's more of administrative function if
you ask me
obviously
okay
all right uh yeah because we have quite
a few lines up actually we'll try to
accommodate all of them as much as
possible uh is there any thought to go
to a deductible plus a no-limit system
mandi has
[Music]
oh no no no no limits uh
with any deductible is not a good option
if you ask me i think uh you have to if
you have to like it's just very simple
you have limited resources you've got to
have some systems do you use them
judiciously and and unlimited
you know excess
there are no doc
the doctors are not available nurses are
not available i mean there is
infrastructure issue you know and there
is so many issues so no amount of
deductible should be you know unlimited
cover
what i would say is that you know when
sometimes people use unlimited maybe
they mean the some insured may not be
limited you know so i think that concept
is possible that if you have you know
some insured need not be talked about
because if you know if everything like
in ayushma bharat is covered but people
never reach the limit of 5 lakh you know
because the way the packages are built
you know is is that people don't you
know reach the limit except in very rare
circumstances so i think to that extent
for the actual beneficiary it is
unlimited but how it is being managed at
the back end is a very different thing
all right uh quickly moving on to the
next question uh pallav sir has asked
can under utilize schemes such as esic
and cdhi they used to extend the pool to
the missing middle esic as we know sits
on a huge under utilized amount this is
only seen as an expense by private
institutions and employers and is poorly
utilized
do you want me to
uh
um
yeah no i think that's something that we
outlined in the second part right that
the possibility of nha pmjy offering
either the existing product or
or a more sort of pmj plus product or of
esic opening up
um
to voluntary contributory so that's a
possibility just the only reason why we
shouldn't rush into it is actually the
problem that you outlined with the
current system the utilization is
actually
very low which has to do
one with supply side challenges but uh
which means that there is the network of
the hospitals the gps the clinics that
they have but also a lot of organization
and management and governance challenges
so there's a separate sort of esic
reform agenda and only i think when that
has been
uh that has been somewhat reformed right
where the claims ratio of how much the
employers and employees are contributing
is actually translating to benefits
currently a lot of people who pay asic
then all have to go and either enroll in
private insurance or go to government
hospitals which then basically means
you're not paying for it uh you're not
paying effectively so the only concern
there is we would want to reform that a
little bit before adding more functions
onto esic uh and burning them with with
a broader mandate but in principle yes
in the sort of in the next five years
you should think about
all it uh quickly i want to talk to uh
deepika had her hand raised uh i think
you were unmuted can you go ahead and
ask your question please
thank you shivangi uh this is dr deepika
sarah for multi-man good evening how are
you
thank you
so anurag your presentation was
wonderful i really liked it a lot of
clarity emerged from it
which i did not have one of them is like
esic the eligibility is you say 21 000.
so this is 20
below 21 000 per annum
per month one month per month wages it's
wages
per month
so what is that what is it for pmga why
i have not
till now understood what is it for pmjy
the eligibility very simple question
but no answer that i've received till
now
yes okay so png is is an entitlement
based scheme
uh you know eligibility is that if you
are in that list of deprivation criteria
there are seven deprivation criterias of
secc you know cast senses uh census 2011
like a heart no you know male member of
the fam family i'm just giving you a
couple of examples
those are listed people who are listed
as the households which are listed in
that list are automatically eligible so
they are automatically used then there
are in the urban urban
settings there are you know certain
professions occupational like mains
drivers gardeners the whole issue dr
saraf is is the awareness among these
people who have become entitled
overnight you know so so i mean if if 40
50 crore people who are there in that
list for there is a data issue because
now it's a 10 year old
census data so the data itself you know
has a lot of null household ids
and so and then people who are actually
there are actually a
huge number of them are not aware that
they have become entitled to the scheme
so then them coming forward and availing
benefits is a second challenge third
that you know it's a it's a dynamic data
people keep more you know people more
people might have moved into poverty
into those category and some might have
moved out of those categories
and so the data is not matching up you
know with the current scenario so these
are some of the issues but i think
who is covered is very clearly defined
and i'll be happy to share the link for
that you know yeah
now thank you very much i mean thank you
very much for this i will be very happy
to go through it i mean i mean please
try and understand from the user
perspective how complicated it may be
for a person to come to the scheme
whether he's or she's eligible after you
know i have studied statistics
biostatistics done my doctorate in
community medicine from ames after doing
my pediatrics i have not understood it
how can you expect a general citizen of
india to understand it
yeah so uh so you know to make it easy i
think the uh current leadership at nha
and even in the ministry
is you know is coming up like let's put
up a list of people covered at the
village level at the panchayat level
let's take a print out and put the names
of the people so i mean they are there
and there are many ways which are
happening you know then
you know there are some missing you know
families and you know you the state
could actually uh give the names of you
know another vulnerable group instead of
you know if those families are missing
so like that lot of effort is is
happening i'll be happy to you know kind
of clarify on that on a one-to-one basis
please excuse me ma'am but this seems
more complicated than doing a census
i think let's let's connect deepika and
and of course no solution will be 100
you know given the
the scale and you know complexities but
whatever is happening i can definitely
share with you yeah thank you so much
all right thank you uh i'm so sorry we
have already actually run over uh our
time limiter call usually
of course usually it's until eight uh
but we are very happy and excited to see
how many questions we had unfortunately
we will not be able to accommodate all
we have taken a note of all the
remaining questions
uh if any of you have further questions
please email them to us uh the email id
is all hands at first up dot org we will
be very happy to forward them to our
panelists and uh send back their replies
to you uh before we wrap we have one
last announcement
in fact we have
an upcoming health insurance summit from
the confederation of indian industries
the theme is health insurance in india
protecting a billion indians from policy
to action this is a working
conference it's on the 30th of august in
delhi at laramie radio uh registration
link will be provided in the chat box um
for further information you can get in
touch with us once again the conference
is on the 30th of august it's in delhi
and it is offline uh with that uh sadly
we will have to wrap this call on behalf
of uh teams first i would like to thank
all our speakers for joining us today
thank you anurag um for your
presentation uh thank you malty ma'am
thank you sir uh thank you for engaging
with our attendees uh so well the very
aim of our all hands call is that we
want to foster the constructive exchange
of ideas knowledge and solutions to
pressing healthcare problems and i think
we really managed to do that today uh so
once again thank you very much uh we
will see all of you uh next month uh do
join us thank you again
thank you thank you thanks thank you
thank you thank you